[MUSIC]
Stanford University.斯坦福大学
>> All right, well,welcome
to Stanford CS193P,好 欢迎来到斯坦福CS193P
winter of 2015.2015冬季课程
This is lecture number two.这是我们的第二讲
I apologize upfront for my
terrible voice, we are going由于我糟糕的嗓音，预先向大家致歉。今天我们将要
to try to get through this
as best we can today.尽可能去克服这个困难。
Our topics are two fold.我们的话题有两个方面。
[COUGH] We're going to
continue the calculator 我们将继续在上一讲中已经开始的计算器Demo，
demo that we started, in last
lecture and then we're gonna然后我们将会有
have some slides about this
model view controller,一些关于模型视图控制器，
object-oriented design pattern
that we're gonna use in和面向对象设计模式的幻灯片
everything we do.这种设计模式我们已经广泛的使用。
When we build applications
in this class.当我们在这节课中开发应用时
All right?有问题么？
So let's get started
with that demo.没问题就让我开始演示Demo
Again, here's a slide with
the summary of kind of这里是一张总结
the important things
we're gonna talk about.接下去我们即将要讲的重点的幻灯片
You don't need to read
those in advance here,你们并不需要提前去阅读这些
it's more for reference.它便于提供参考。
My slides in general,
I post them,我做的幻灯片一般来讲，
it's mostly intended to almost
be note taking for you.主要是为了方便你们记笔记用
To be able go back and try and为了你们在复习的时候能够
figure out, whoa, when did
he talked about that day?回忆出，哇哦，他什么时候讲过这些？
Oh yeah.哦耶
What's important, et cetera.什么是重要的，等等。
So my slides do tend to
be a little bit dense.所以，我的幻灯片也往往是有点多。
I tend to put a little
more on them, than,我更倾向于多放一些关于这个的内容，
than just bullet items.与项目相比
But that's because I want you
to be able to look back and但是，那是因为我希望你们能够回过头来看的时候
kind of get just a little
bit more depth to对于我所说的
remind yourself what
I talked about.你们更深入的理解
Okay?ok？
All right, so好了，
this demo, if you'll remember
last time, where we left off,关于这个Demo，如果你们还记得上次我们快结束时，
we had gotten the keypad
fully working.我们已经完全实现了计算器的键盘的功能
All right, and we were talking
a little bit about properties我们将要讲一些关于属性和
and instant variables and
how we had to initialize them.实例变量相关的内容，以及如何去初始化它们
And so I'm gonna ask
a question right at我将会在这讲结束的时候问一个问题
the end of lecture,
perfect timing.多完美的时机
What about the little
outlet that we dragged out为什么我们拖出的
that display UI label
exclamation point, how come we显示UI Lable的outlet后面有个感叹号
didn't have to make that
equal to something, to start.以及为什么我们从一开始不需要将它赋值
And that's where this
demo is gonna pick up.我们将从这个地方继续上次的Demo
Okay?OK？
>> Okay.ok
[COUGH] Well, let's dive back
into this demonstration,好吧，让我们深入到演示中来
where we left off.接着我们上次讲的地方
Which it was this
line of code, here.上次我们在这行代码结束的
And, we had just talked about
the fact that we have to我们之前讲过我们必须
initialize all of our
variables [COUGH] in a class,在类中初始化我们的变量
in any class.在任何类中都必须这样做
And, so that's why we need
this equals falls here.所以我们需要在这个加个等号
They wanted the equal falls
too but we needed it and yet这里也需要等号赋值，但是
it didn't seem like
we needed one here.这里看起来并不需要等号赋值
And why was that?为什么会是这样？
Well, it turns out
that this right here,好吧，事实证明，在这里
even though it doesn't quite
look like one, is an optional.即使它看起来不完全像之前那个，这是一个optional
And, optionals automatically
get equaled nil, given to you.而且optionals在你使用之前就赋了nil
So, you don't actually have
to put the equals nil here.所以，其实你们并不需要在这里给它赋nil
So that's why, so this one
here is getting initialized.这就是为什么这里已经初始化了
It's just being done
automatically for you.它都自动帮你做好了
But, let's talk about
the look of this thing.但是，我们来谈论一下这个东西的样子
It's got this
exclamation point here.在这里有个感叹号
And, if it were an optional,如果它是一个optional
you'd be used to it
having a question mark.你们通常会在这里看到一个问号
For example, we look at
this optional right here,例如，我们来看这里这个optional
current title,current title,
you see it's string question
mark not exclamation point,你们将会看到这里string是问号而不是感叹号
question mark.这里是问号
So what's the difference
between a question mark and那么，在问号和感叹号之间
an exclamation point here?有什么区别？
And the answer is,答案是
it makes no difference to
the actual type, it's still对于实际类型而言它们没有区别，
an optional whose value
here could be a UI label.它仍然是一个optional，其值在这里可能是一个UI label类型。
But it matters on
the usage of it.但是它的区别在于它的用法上
[COUGH] And
this is purely just kind of这完全是编译器
a compiler helping
you out thing, here.帮你把这事做掉了
But if we look at
when I change this to但是如果我们将这个感叹号
a question mark you see that
some errors appear down here.改成问号。Xcode将会在这里报出一些错误提示
So then let's click on one of
these errors, like this one,那么，让我们点击这其中的一个错误提示，比如说这个
and you can see
the errors that UI label,你们将会看到UI label控件
question mark does not
have a member named text.问号没有叫text的成员变量
In other words you
can't send text.换句话说，你不能将text赋给
UI label question mark,UI label问号
which is what this is and that
makes sense because UI label因为UI label后面这个问号
question mark is
an optional and是一个optional，而且
obviously an optional
doesn't respond to text.很显然这个optional不是回应text的
UI labels do, but
optionals don't.UI label是这样的，但optional不一定这样
So, why are we getting
this error now when we那么，为什么我们会这出错
weren't getting it before.在这之前却没有
And how would we get
rid of this error?我们又如何去避免这个错误？
Well, you could
certainly get rid of好了，我们当然可以通过
this error by just putting
an exclamation point here,添加一个感叹号来避免这个错误
that would unwrap
this optional.它将会去除这个optional
And now this would be
an UI label right here and那么现在这里会变成UI label，而且
we can send a text.我们可以将text赋值给它
And we do the same
thing up here.我们在这里也做同样的操作
We can unwrap it there and
we can unwrap it there.我们可以在这里去除它，也可以在那里去除它
And that gets rid of
all of our errors.这样一来避免了所有同样的错误
But [COUGH] this kind of an
interesting property in that但是这里有个很有意思的属性
even though it's
not initialized in即使它并没有初始化
the very beginning of
a colossus creation starts out在庞大得创建方法中
as nil not set.都没有对其赋nil
As soon as as this user
interface gets loaded up只要这个接口被加载了
by this new controller.通过新的控制器
Then this gets wired up,
alright, so, that gets那么这个将连接起来，好了，那么那里
wired up, and this is set, and
then this it's set forever.也将连接起来，只要这里被赋值了，那么所有的这个都被赋值了
So it's really, kinda would
be sad if we actually,假如这是真的，那么当我们每次在用的时候
every time we used it had
to unwrap it all the time.我们都将加上感叹号，这真是挺悲伤的
So these kind of
properties that.所以这些属性
Get set very early, maybe
not right at creation like很早就被赋值的，不一定像这个一样是正确地创建
this one, but very,
they get set very early, and但是，绝大部分还是会在创建的时候就赋值
then they stay
set all the time.然后之后就一直被赋值
You can, instead of你也可以
putting a question mark
in their decoration.在声明的地方加一个问号来代替
We're talking about
their decoration here.我们将在这里谈论他们的声明
You can put
an exclamation point.你们可以在这里加一个感叹号
And what that says is.那么它会提示你
This is just an optional, but这只是一个optional，但是
always automatically unwrap
it so that you don't have to它会自动解开为了让你不用
put this exclamation
point in here.在这里加感叹号
So I take this
exclamation point out.所以，我把这里的感叹号删掉了
You can see, it's not
generating any errors.你们可以看到，它将不再报错
And it's still going to
unwrap this display and它将把display转化成
turn into a UI label.UI label
And.而且
It's still gonna crash
your program if for它还是会奔溃由于
some reason
the display were nil.某些原因比如display是nil
If you tried to execute
this code, that may如果你执意要执行这段代码，那是
be impossible because this
is the button sending those.不可能的，因为这里是由按钮来发送这些的
So the button wouldn't be here
if this hadn't gotten already这个按钮不会在这里除非它加载的时候
loaded up in the set.被赋值
But if somehow you had some
place in your controller or但是如果在某种情况下你必须
you were accessing display
before this UI got loaded.在UI加载之前你要获取display
It would crash,
because it is unwrapping this,它将奔溃，因为它还没有解开联系
it's just that you don't have
to put the explanation point,你不需要在这里写感叹号
it's kinda like auto
explanation point.它会自动解析
And, this is called a
implicitly unwrapped optional.这个就叫做unwrapped optional
Okay?
Implicitly unwrapped optional.有问题嘛？隐式unwrapped optional
And it's really only useful
for this kind, of property,在这种情况下它真的很有用对于属性来说
that's, set very early, and
then stay set, forever.在创建的时候就赋值，那么将一直被赋值
It's kind of sugar, really.这真是一个好的语法糖
Okay, so let's move on好了，我们将继续
to the next button in
our [INAUDIBLE] here.接着下一个按钮
Which is going to
be an enter button.它就是Enter键
Now our calculator does
not have an equals sign.现在我们的计算器还没有等号
So you're probably used
to calculators where you你们也许通常会这样使用计算器
say six plus three then when
you hit equals it shows you6乘以3，然后你们按等号计算器展示
the result.结果
This calculator is我们的计算器会
a little more like
a scientific calculator.更像科学计算器
Has an enter key.将没有等号按钮
And so, instead you put
the numbers you want to add or那么，你们按你们想相加的数字按钮或者
divide or multiply or whatever
onto a stack and then when you除以或者乘以无论什么都将会入栈，然后当你
press the operation keys it
pulls them off the stack.按下操作按钮的时候，数字将会出栈
So that looks like this,
6 enter 3 times.比如这样 6 乘以 3
Four, six, enter,
three, enter, times.46 乘以 3
So the times is going
to pull the six and这个乘法操作符将会把6 和
the three off the stack.3 出栈
You could even go six, enter,
five, enter, four, enter, and你也可以按6，？，5， ？4？然后
then go times plus.按乘以
That would multiply the top
two on the stack and它将会把栈顶的两个元素出栈
then add the last one on.操作完再将加上栈顶的元素
So we need an enter key
here for our calculator.所以我们的计算器还是需要一个Enter键
Now, I'm gonna create that
enter key in a way that's 现在，我将要通过这种方式创建一个enter键
actually gonna cause a problem
for me in a moment, but它虽然会引起一些问题，但是
I wanna show you how to
resolve that very problem.我将会展示给你们看如何解决这些问题
So I'm gonna create this enter
key by copying and pasting.那么，我将通过复制粘贴
This digit key right here.这里的数字键来创建Enter键
And I'm just gonna
put it in here.那么我将会把这段代码放在这里
Notice that I'm lining these,注意我要粘贴在这里
blue lines up
absolutely perfectly.蓝色的辅助线出现最好
I don't want them to be, like
it's lined up with that one,我不想这些按钮像这个一样
but not that one or
vice versa.或者那个一样
I want them
perfectly lined up.我希望它完全对齐
Cuz later I'm gonna spread
these out over the whole UI因为我待会要在整个UI中放大这些按钮
and if I haven't lined these
up just absolutely perfectly如果我没有将这些按钮对齐的话
then Expo's not gonna quite
know what I want here inXcode将不会知道我想把它放在这里
terms of the relationship
between these.在这个和这个之间
All right so we don't want a
three on here, we want to have好了，我们不希望这个按钮上还是3，所以我们需要修改一下
a,enter symbol so I'm gonna go
up here to special characters.一个enter的符号，我将输入一个特殊的符号
This is on in most
Mac applications.这个符号在很多的Mac应用中都有
You can go to the edit menu
to get special characters.你们可以从编辑菜单中获取这些特殊符号
And I'm going to search for我想要搜索
this one actually, I think
that's called a return.这个特殊符号，我觉得它应该叫返回
Yeah.
And these are just是的，这些都是
Unicode characters right here.Unicode字符
And so
I want this one that looks,我想要这个
kind of like a return or
enter key.看起来像返回或者enter按钮的
So I have this.好了，我找到了
And I'm gonna use the same
mechanism we used before,我将使用之前使用过的机制
which is CTRL+drag.那就是CTRL+drag
So I'm just gonna
CTRL+drag out here.那么我想CTRL+drag拖到这里
And, we're creating an action,然后，我们创建一个action
of course, cuz we want this
button to send us a message.当然，我们希望这个按钮传递给我们一个信息
I'm gonna call it Enter.我讲叫它Enter
That's what it is
the answer key那就是我们的返回键.
Now one thing is
different about this one,现在有一件事会有一点不同
if you'll remember when
we wired this action up,如果你记得当我们连接这个action的时候
we had the button that was
sending it as an argument and我们让这个按钮传递给我们一个参数
we don't want that this time.但是我们这次不需要这么做
Because there's only
one answer key we因为这里只有一个返回键
really don't need to talk
back to the answer key, so我们并不需要让返回键传参，所以
we're going to say
none right here.我们在这里不需要参数
It also doesn't really matter
about this type because we're这里我们更不用关心它的类型，因为
not going to have
an argument so我们这里并不需要参数
it doesn't matter
what this type is.不用管它这里是什么类型
So disconnect that.那么先断开他们的连接
As you can see right here.你们可以看这里
We have Enter, and
it has no arguments.我们已经有一个enter键，没有参数的
Now, what are we gonna
do inside Enter?那么现在，我们将在这个Enter里做什么操作？
Well, the main thing
we need to do is,好吧，我们主要要做的是
put whatever number is
in this display up here,把所有的数字在这里加起来
okay, onto our internal stack.ok.在我们的栈中
So, we're gonna need那么，我们需要
an internal stack,
in a moment, here.一个暂时的栈
Another thing we
might wanna do, is.另一件我们想做的事
Set users in the middle of
typing the number to false.设置用户中间操作数字这个参数为false
Because we might have
been typing a number, but因为我们可能已近输入了一个数字
as soon as we hit enter,
we're putting it on the stack.但是，只要我们单击enter键，我们将把数字放入栈中
Next time we type a digit,接下来我们再输入一个数字
we're going to be
starting a new number.我们将输入一个新的数字
[COUGH] All right, so we'll
call that user [NOISE] in好了，那么我们就叫它 输入好了
the middle of
typing falls there.中间输入那里
Now, let's go ahead and,
and actually run this and现在，让我们继续，运行这个
see how this is working.看看它是怎么工作的
Because there's going to
be a little problem here.因为这里有个小问题
So, run this.那么，先运行一下
Alright, so
let's try eight, enter.好了，让我们试一下输入8，然后enter
Oh.Oh
What's that?
Oh, my god.那是什么？上帝啊
Six, enter.6，然后 enter键
Well it's, it's kind of
working because after we好吧，它能运行因为我们
press enter the user is in
the middle of typing numbers.按了enter键，the user is in the middle of typing numbers参数
Starts over.重新开始
So that's good, but
I had no intention for所以这是好的，但是我并不想
this to be showing up on
the end of my display.让这个在最后显示出来
This little enter.这个enter
What the heck is
that doing on there?这个heck是做什么的？
Why is that happening?为什么会发生这样的事
Let's take a look here.让我们看看这里
The problem here, has to do
with the messages being sent.问题出在这里，在信息传递之前
So, when we wire this up,
that's good.那么，当我们连接好了，它就好了
We got enter.我们已经有enter键了
The problem is that button
also sends a pen digit.问题是那个按钮还传递数字
That's because we copied and
pasted this three, remember?那是因为我们复制粘贴的3的按钮，记得么？
And the three sends a pen
digit, until we copy and而3按钮还传递了一个数字，直到我们复制
paste it.粘贴了它
Now, this one sends,
sends a pen digit.现在 ，这个按钮传递了一个数字
So this is both.而且这个也是
Okay, sending two.ok，传递了两次
Now, that's a common
mistake to make.现在，这是一个很常见的错误
You know, you only think
about that when you copy and你们知道么，你们不会去想这些当你们复制
paste it.粘贴它
And how do we fix this?那么我们如何来修复这个问题？
Well if you right click, so好了，如果你们右击一下
I'm going to right
click on this button.我将右键一下这个按钮
You'll get this
window that comes up.你们将会看到这个窗口
And it shows you all
the connections from this然后你们可以看到所有的连接
UY element to your code.UY元素到你们的代码
And you can see here
both appendage and你们可以看到这里都连接
enter are connected.enter键
The great thing is I can just
click this little X right here最棒的事我可以点击这里的X按钮
and it'll take this
connection away.然后这个连接就被取消了
So now I only have enter.那么，现在我们只有enter键的连接了
So now if I go back here.那么现在我们再回到之前的地方
See it's,看这里
it's not sending appendage,
it is sending enter.它将不再传递附加物，它只传递enter
And you can do this right
clicking for anything.你们可以右键操作任何你们想做的
Like we need to do it for
our label up here.就像我们必须连接label一样
See there's the display
connection we have right here.看到没，这里显示了我们的连接
So don't forget right click
to disconnect things.不要忘记右键去除连接
Now if you forget about
this and you don't do it.现在，如果你们忘记这个，你们不要去操作它
Or maybe you have it wired to
some thing that you change.否则你们会连接一些你们修改的东西
For example, if we have
accidentally put an argument比如，我们需要传递一个参数
here to enter, if we had made
it do descending button trick,对于enter键来说，如果我们已经做过了
kind of like this.像这样的
You can't just say, oh okay.你们不能说好的
I'll fix that.我将会修复它的
I'll just delete that我将会删除它的.
Because that would
not work because,因为它将会不工作
enter with an argument
is actually a different因为带有参数的enter键它是不同的
message than enter
with no argument.对于没参数的enter键来说
And so, if you just deleted
that when you were running如果你们在运行的时候删除了这些
your program it
would crash and你的应用将会奔溃
it would say, couldn't
send message enter colon.它会说，enter不能传递参数
When you touch this button
cause enter colon means enter当你点击enter键的时候
with an argument, only for the
purpose of this tour It doe-,
we don't see enter
colon in our code.我们看不到enter的代码
That's just something that's,
this story board here.还好这里有story board
So if that happens, you need
to right click on here and那么如果这个发生了，你必须点击这里
disconnect the enter colon,
that happened in there and去除连接，然后再重新
then you just recontrol drag.拖拉连接
When you recontrol
drag it's nice it will.当你重新连接好，它会变正常了
Kind of let you try to
grab onto something, so让你们尝试一下
its easy to reconnect.它很容易重新连接。
Kay?OK？
All right, so now we want to
actually implement enter here.好了，那么现在我们在这里实现这个方法
We want to enter
the guts of it.
我们开始着手实现它的内部。
And so we are going to need
another property here which is
我们需要在这定义另一个属性，
going to be that
它将会是
internal stack that these
numbers are going to go on.
这些数字的内部栈。
And so that's gonna
be a var just like
所以它会是一个变量，就像
this var up here that
we've created and
我们刚创建的这个变量。
I'm call it operand stack
that's a good name for it.
我叫它操作符栈，不错的名字。
And it's gonna have a type,
它会有一个类型，
it's type is going
to be an array and
它的类型是数组，
just like in other languages
like Java when you specify,
就像在其他语言中，比如说Java——
when you create an array
type you have to specify.
当你创建一个数组，你必须指明它的类型，
What kind of thing
is in the array.
表明数组里面存储的是什么。
And so, I'm gonna put
doubles in my array.
因此，我打算在里面存放double元素
And that's, even though you
might say, well we can't
嗯。也许你会说，好吧我们并不能
enter doubles, because these
are all integers, basically.
输入double，因为这里大都是些integer。
But if I were to say,
3 enter 6 divide, I get .5.
但是假如我说，输入3除以6，我会得到0.5，
So than a double would appear.
这样就出现了一个double。
So that's why I'm
going to use double.
这就是我为什么要使用double。
Now, you can see that we've
got this error up here again.
现在，你们可以看到这里又弹出了这个错误，
It says stored property
operandStack does not
上面说存储的属性operandStack并没有
have initial value.
初始值。
So we have to give
this an initial value.
所以我们得赋给它初始值。
So I'm going to give
this an initial value of
我准备把初始值赋为
an empty array.
一个空的数组。
So now you're seeing for the
first time how you actually.
现在你们第一次看到实际上如何
Create an instance of
a class or of a data type.
创建一个类或者数据类型的实例。
And you do that just by
specifying the type and
你只需要在这指明类型
then use parenthesis.
然后写上分号。
Now, we're not,
现在，我们没有，
again we haven't talked
about initializers.
我们还没有讨论过构造器。
A class or
一个类或者
a data structure can have
multiple initializers.
一种数据类型可以有许多构造器。
Some of them might
have arguments in here.
其中的一些可能会在这里有参数。
But most, if it's possible
they'll allow you to
但大多数情况，如果允许，你都可以
create them with no
arguments and in a case on
创建没有参数的构造器，对于
our right(!!array，我听的是这个，请校验) it's very
obvious what to do.
数组，该做什么一目了然。
No arguments just creates
an empty array right,
不需要参数，只要创建一个空的数组，在右边
with no elements in it.
这里不需要任何参数。
Now, one thing I want to talk
about is this right here.
现在，我想说一下这里这个东西，
This type, you know?
这种类型，你们知道吗，
It's kind of annoying that
we have to type this and
你会觉得很烦，如果在这定义了类型，
then we have to type
it right again.
然后在这又得定义一遍。
And the answer is,
we don't have to do that,
而事实上，我们并不需要这么做，
because in swift,
swift is very strongly typed.
因为swift是严格强类型的。
You know there's all
the variables, but
你要知道所有的变量，
the properties
are strongly typed.
属性都是强类型的。
But they, there's also
a lot of type inference.
而且它们都有许多类型推断。
So swift can infer.（此处应该没有句号，this type应该在这里）
因此swift可以推断类型。
This type in the exact same
way that digit had no type and
比如说这里的digit并没有类型，
it inferred it from here.
但它可以从这里推断出来。
OperandStack, we don't have
to specify they type, and
OperandStack，我们并不需要指明它的类型，因为
it can infer it from here.
可以从这里推断出来。
And if we option click on
operandStack you'll see that
如果我们按住option点击operandStack，你会看到
indeed, it's figured out that
that's an array of double.
它确实可以辨识出这是一个double类型的数组。
And in fact,
事实上，
putting the type in here
is considered bad form.
在这里指明类型被认为是不好的书写形式。
If it can be inferred,
you should let it infer, so,
如果可以推断出类型，你就应该让它自己去推断，所以
if we didn't have this blue（for example，而且明明是bool！英文是机器录入的么） up
here we shouldn't that either,
拿这里的Bool来说，我们其实也需要声明类型。
because, false, and true are,
can only be blue values so,（bool！！！）
因为false和true只可能是Bool的值。
we're gonna take
that off as well.
所以我们也可以把它去掉。
Okay, so, now, our brand（operand好伐，我真是醉了，好累）
好了，那么现在，我们这里有操作符栈，
stack right here what
do we wanna do with it?
我们打算把怎么处理它呢？
Well, when we press enter,
we just want to append.
嗯，我们按下回车，然后我们想要append，
So, append.
所以，append。
This is actually the first
time we're sending an actual
事实上这是我们第一次发送一条
message to an object
looks just like when we
消息给一个对象。就像去
accessed a property.
获取了一个属性一样。
The dot and it's just the name
of the method that we're
输入点号，然后就出现了我们想要在数组上调用的方法名字。
trying to invoke
in our arrays.
Just an array, an array method
right here called a pen（append！！）.
这是一个数组；这是一个叫做append的数组方法。
I think you see the arguments
as newElement: T.
我想你们看到了这个参数——newElement: T
This : T means it has
to be of this type.
这个 : T 意味着它必须是这个类型。
Type of things in the array so
this has to be a double.
这个数组里面东西的类型，所以它必须是一个double。
So that's kind of a problem,
cuz really what I want to
这也是一个问题，因为事实上我想要在
append onto my stack is what's
up here in this display text.
我的栈上附加的是，这里display text的内容。
And, you know, I'd like to
say something along the lines
然后在这行输入display.text
of display.text.
Okay?
But what type is this?
好吧，它的类型是什么呢？
I can type display.text.（type of display.text？？）
display.text的类型。
Now that's not string.
它不是string。
That is an optional.
它是一个optional。
Remember that display.text
is an optional.
记住这里的display.text是一个optional，
So we can unwrap
it even though
所以我们可以把它拆包，但
that's not gonna
solve the problem.
这并不能解决问题。
This is still a string and
这仍是一个string，
you're still seeing
an error here.
你们还是可以看到这里有一个错误。
The same string is not
convertible to double [COUGH].
这个string不可以转化为double[咳]。
Because we're supposed
to be putting doubles in
因为我们本应把double放入
this array putting strings.
这个数组而不是string。
So, we have a problem here.
所以，我们在这有个问题。
We have somehow to convert
this string into a double so
我们得用某种方式把string转化成double以便
we can put it on this stack.
我们把它放入栈中。
I'm gonna use
this opportunity.
我要借用这个机会，
Just show you another
feature which we
向你们展示另一个特性，我们
call Computed Properties.
称之为计算型属性。
So I'm gonna create another
property display value and
所以我要在这里创建另一个属性displayValue,
it's gonna be a double.
它是一个double。
And what I want this to be
equal to is, I always want it
然后我想让它等于，我想让它
to be whatever's in this
display converted to a double.
等于这里的显示转化成double的值。
Okay?
And I want to
好了，然后我想
be able to set it or get it so
有办法对它进行设值以及取值，以便
I'm gonna be able to get
the value of this double.
我能够取到这个double的值。
I just want to be able to
set it as a double and
我想把它设值成一个double然后
have it turn into text.
把它转化成文本。
Well, that kind of
好吧，这种类型的
property really is tied to
some data somewhere else.
属性实际上是与其他地方的某些数据绑定的。
So, I don't ever want to set
it equal to some initial value
所以，我不想把它设成某个初始值
or something.
还是什么。
Really, I want it to always be
calculated and we can do that.
实际上，我想让它总是可计算的，而我们可以做到。
Instead of saying
equals something,
与其说等于什么，
you just put curly
braces after.
你只需要在后面写上大括号。
And you say, get,
and we say, set.
然后写下get，再写set。
Okay?
好了。
And inside here we are gonna
compute the value of this.
然后在这里面，我们要对它的值进行计算了。
Which is we are gonna
convert this display text
这将会把这里的显示文本转化成
to a double and then inside
here, we are, someone said,
double，然后在这里，我们要，要让
display value equal something
and we are going to
显示值等于什么，我们要做的是
somehow compute,
not really compute it, but.
想办法能够计算它，并不是真的去计算“它”，而是
We're gonna de, decide,
what code we need to put that
我们要决定我们需要什么样的代码能够把
number that they tried to set
the display value to in here.
那个显示值在这里设值。
'Kay, so
let's do the set side first.
好吧，那么让我们先来写set方法。
It's actually
a little simpler.
这其实会简单一些。
Inside this set,
在set方法里，
there's a magic variable
called new value.
会有一个叫作newValue的魔法变量，
It doesn't, it's not purple
for some reason, but.
它不是，因为某些原因它并不是紫色的
New value in this,
this is the new value.
这里的newValue。
So if someone says
somewhere in our code,
如果说在我们的代码里，
display value equals five,
显示值等于5，
this new value will
have the five.
那这个newValue就会是5。
And so all I really wanna do。
我所想做的
here is say display text
equals the new value.
就是在这让display.text等于newValue。
But again, of course this
is an optional string.
但同样的问题，这是个optional string，
You can't set it to a double
because displayValue equals
你不能把它设成一个double因为displayValue等于
five, this new values
going to be a double.
5，这个newValue将会是一个double。
But we know how to convert
something to a string by
但是我们知道如何把它转化成string，只需要写上
using backlash parenthesis.
反斜线，圆括号。
And this is the same
thing we did when we
这其实和我们
printed out [COUGH]
our digit up here.
输出[咳]这里digit是一样的。
We just use the back
slash parenthesis.
我们只需要写上反斜线和圆括号。
It tries to convert
this thing inside here,
它会试着在这里转化这个东西，
which is a double into
a string of doubles.
把一个double转化成string。
You know how to do
that themselves.
你知道该怎么做了。
And so bingo,
we've got our display text and
没错。我们得到了display.text，
that's all that necessary.
这就够了。
also, every time someone sets
this value and then we're
而且，每次有人设值时，很明显我们
clearly not in the middle
of typing a number anymore.
不再是在输入一个数字了。
[INAUDIBLE] Say that.
说。
[INAUDIBLE] All right,
what about the getting?
好吧，那关于取值呢？
Now in the getting
all we have to do is
在取值方法中，我们所要做的就是
return this display value.
返回displayValue。
So it's do something
to calculate what this
就是要去计算
display value is here.
这里的displayValue。
And then return it.
然后返回它。
Now this one I'm not
gonna take time to go
这次我不会花时间去
through the details here.
详细说明细节。
And actually I've made it an
extra credit item that you can
实际上我把它算作一个给你们去做的额外加分项，
do, which requires
you to figure out
需要你们利用文档，去搞清楚我要在这写什么，
what I'm gonna type here
using the documentation.
But I'm not going
to explain it here.
而我不会在这解释它。
I'm gonna use a class that's
in this number formatter.
我要在这个使用一个叫作NumberFormatter的类
I'm actually gonna
create one and
我先创建一个，然后
I'm gonna use a method on it
called number from string.
我要使用它的一个方法叫numberFromString。
And I'm gonna give it
this string which is
然后我会把这个string传给他，
the display values text,
unwrapped of course.
display.text,当然得拆包。
The result is acting optional
so I'm gonna unwrap that.
结果是一个optional，所以我要把它拆包。
And then I'm gonna get the
double value of the thing I
然后我要得到它返回的的double值。
get back [COUGH].
[咳]
Number gives me this
kind of generic number so
Number给了我这种泛型的数字，所以
I am gonna take it and
turn it into a double.
我把它转化成一个double。
So there we go.
好了。
So you can go
the next spread and
你们可以继续下一步了，
look at that later
if you want.
以后再考虑它，如果你想的话。
But surprising to say we
高兴的是我们
now have a property display
value that when we set it and
现在有了一个displayValue的属性，我们可以调用set和
get it, it's gonna be
setting and getting.
get方法来设值和取值。
It has a string here, so
that is really convenient.
这里有一个string，所以它也挺方便的。
Especially for
尤其是这里，
right here, where we
wanna say display value.
其实我们想写的是displayValue
'Kay?
好。
So let's see the double.
让我们来看看这个double
No problem.
没错。
We're pinning that
onto operandStack.
我们把它附到operandStack上了。
So let's print in our
operandStack here.
所以让我们把operandStack在这打印出来。
Just so, I mean we can do the
same thing here, operandStack.
就像这样，一样的方式，operandStack。
Okay?
And this worked because
operandStack is an array, and
这种方式可行是因为operandStack是一个数组，
arrays know how to turn
themselves into strings.
数组是知道如何把他们自身转化成string的。
You'll see how they do that in
the console in a moment here.
你一会儿就会在console里看到它们是怎么做到的了。
So let's go ahead and
所以我们继续
see if our application is
actually putting things on
来看看我们的程序是否真的正确地能够把东西放到
our stack properly here.
我们的栈里。
[NOISE]
All right.
好的。
Let's try here.
我们试着在这里，
Let's try 56 enter.
在这里输入56，
And look, operandStack
equals 56 doing good.
看，operandStack是等于56，运行正常。
Seven enter.
输入7，
All right, 56.0 and 7.0.
好的，56.0和7.0。
So, you can see that arrays
turn themselves into strings
所以你们看到了数组是如何把自身转化成string的，
by doing open square bracket
and then they turn each of
在这个方括号里，它们把自身的每个
their elements into strings
and separated by commas.
元素转化成string并以逗号分隔。
Now this is good.
这个就搞定了。
So we got our operand,
operandStack building here.
我们这的operandStack就创建好了。
So all we need to do is have
some times, and plus, and
所以我们现在需要做的就是要有乘法，加法和
minus buttons, et cetera.
减法之类的按钮。
I'm gonna put them right here.
我要把他们放在这里。
That will operate on these
items uh,on the stack.
它在在这些项上进行运算，在栈上。
So, if I pressed
plus right now,
所以，如果我现在按下加，
it would pull the seven and
the eight off the stack.
它就会把7和8从栈中拉出来，
Add them together,
it would be 15.
把他们相加，得到15。
Show that 15 here, and
在这里显示15，
it actually will put
the 15 back on the stack.
实际上15会被放回到栈里。
So then, we'd have 56 and
15 on our stack.
然后，我们的栈里就有了56和15。
Then we could, maybe.
接着我们就可以，
Plus those together and
we wanted by it plus again.
把它们加到一起，再运行一次加法。
All right?
没错吧？
[COUGH] Okay.
好的。
So how are we gonna do that?
所以我们应该怎么做呢？
Well, we would make
our buttons here.
嗯，我们把按钮放到这。
And I'm gonna make the buttons
again by copying and
我通过复制粘贴数字按钮来创建这些按钮。
pasting a digit button.
But this time I know
about that problem,
但是这次我已经知道那个问题了，
so right off the bat I'm
gonna right click on it.
所以马上就点击它。
And disconnect appendage it.（appendDigit。。。）
然后取消和appendDigit的关联。
Okay?
So
好的，那么
now this button sends no
messages, yet anyway.
这个按钮现在就不会发送任何消息了。
And then we could
put a type on here.
然后我们要在这上面设置一个符号。
So here I'm gonna have my all
my operations buttons use
这里我要让所有的运算按钮使用
mathematical symbols so if we
go down here to math symbols.
数学符号，所以我们看这里的math symbols。
See there's a bunch
of math symbols here.
看这里有好多数学符号。
So let's do times, right here,
我们来给乘法设置符号，就在这里。
first, we'll put times right
there, and we can wire it up.
首先，把乘法放到这，然后我们可以把他嵌入代码。
I'm just gonna hold that
Ctrl and drag out here.
按住Ctrl然后拉到这里来。
We're gonna call
this action method.
我们把这个action称作方法
Operate.
operate。
And because I'm gonna have
multiple operation buttons and
因为会有许多运算按钮，而且
they're all going
to send operate.
他们都会发送operate。
Just like I did
with append digit,
就像附加digit一样，
I am going to use the sender.
我要使用这个sender，
So I'm gonna be very
careful to change this any
所以我得仔细地
object to be button.
把这个按钮上的anyObject改称UIButton。
Do not forget that.
不要忘记这点。
'Kay, so action,
we are gonna have it centered.(set sender!!)
好了，action，设置好的sender。
UIButton.
UIButton。
Call it operate.
operate。
There it is.
就是这样。
That's method doing operate.
这就是operate方法。
We can copy and
paste this button now, right?
我们现在可以复制粘贴按钮了。
We got this one, so
我们用这个，
let's copy and paste and
make some more of these.
让我们复制粘贴然后重复。
We'll start out with
four of them, let's say.
我们先搞出4个。
'Kay?
好。
Let's get back our
special characters here.
我们回到特殊符号这里。
[COUGH] All right, so
let's make this one be divide.
[咳]好的，我们来把它做成除法。
Let's make this one plus.
我们把这个做成加法。
And this one be minus.
这个是减法。
All right.
好了。
So we've got these
buttons [COUGH].
按钮就完成了。
And they're all sending,
if we look at this here,
它们都会发送，如果我们看这里，
they're all sending operate.
它们都会发送operate。
Luckily, they're not sending
anything except operate, so
幸运的是它们并不会发送运算之外的东西，
that's good.
这样刚好。
And when they send operate,
we're gonna figure out
当他们发送operate的时候，我们要搞清楚
which one is sending it by the
same exact way we did above.
哪个是按照我们之前的方式去发送的。
We're gonna say what is
the sender's current title?
sender的currentTitle是什么？
We're gonna unwrap it.
我们要把它拆包。
So operation here is
gonna be a string.
这里的operation是一个string。
And it's going to tell us
the title of the buttons so
它会告诉我们按钮的title，所以
we know which one
to use there.
我们就知道了该用哪个。
Now I'm gonna show you a
control flow operator here in
现在我要给你们展示swfit中的控制流符号，
Swift that's very powerful,
much more powerful than
它非常强大，比其他语言中的强大多了。
this operator is in
other languages.
And also very,
very important to switch.（swift）
而且对Swfit来说很重要。
I'm only gonna show you the
simplest usage of it here, but
这里我只会向你们展示它的最简单用法，但是
you're gonna see on
Monday's demonstration and
你们会在周一的展示和
later in the quarter how
important this operator is.
接下来的一个季度感受到它的强大。
But, it's switch, okay, and
它是就switch，而且
switch looks like switch
in other languages, like C.
它和其他语言中的switch看起来很像，比如C。
You switch on something.
你在某种东西上switch。
In this case I'm gonna
switch on this string.
这里我会在string上switch。
This is the string.
这就是那个string，
Then you just specify
the case of each thing.
然后你要指明所有case。
So for
example here I have a case.
所以举例来说，有一个case，
Let's do the multiply.
进行乘法，
Okay, so we've got
multiply case right here.
这就是一个乘法case，
And then we just put
the code that we want here
接着我们把需要的代码放到这里，
for multiply.
做乘法。
And we'd do that for
all the other cases here.
接着对其他的case也这么做。
So let's copy and paste.
复制然后粘贴。
And we'll do this
be our divide case.
这个是除法case，
And we'll have this
be our plus case and
这个是加法case，
we'll have this be our,
这个是，
make sure we're doing the same
[INAUDIBLE] here, plus case.
要确保方式一致，加法
Again, you've got to be
a little careful here.
这里你们又得仔细一点了，
You know, this minus is
slightly different from this
这里的减法符号是和
minus which might be slightly
different than the minus
这个减法符号和
you type with the keyboard.
你们键盘上输入的减法符号是有一些不同的。
So, when you're putting
the symbols here,
所以，当你们在这放置这个符号的时候，
you wanna use exactly the same
symbols here in your case.
你们要确定使用的是同一个符号。
Now, one thing about Switch
on Swift though is it
关于Swift的Switch的要注意的一件事就是
absolutely requires that you
have every case covered.
你必须确保覆盖所有情况。
Now since this is a string,
obviously can't have case of
由于这是一个字符串,显然不可能
every single string
in the universe.
穷举每一种情况
That is almost infinite,
but luckily there,
通常是无限多的,但是很幸运的是,
you can take defaults and
just break out of the switch.
可以再default后,使用break跳出switch
That means if it's not one of
these cases by default just
也就是如果不是上面列举的情况,
break out of the switch.
就会默认跳出switch语句
You could put code
here as well,
代码也可以放在这里
but breaking out of it is
what we wanna do in our case.
在需要的地方break
now, in here, we're just going
to put the code for multiply.
现在,在这里,放乘法相关的语句
So, what do we need to do for
multiply?
那么,乘法需要做些什么?
For the moment,
I'm gonna comment this out.
我会暂时将这部分注视掉
I'm gonna use command, slash,
使用command + / 来注释
which is a really
nice feature.
这种注释方法的确称得上是一个很不错的功能.
You do command slash.
command + /之后,
And then command slash again,
to uncomment.
再次command + /来取消给代码注释.
[INAUDIBLE] real quick cuz I
just wanna focus on times.
这样就可以专注于当前的事情上,
Now any time I
press any operator,
任何时候,点击任何操作符,
I probably wanna give
the user an automatic enter.
可能会给用户自动按下enter键
That's so that six enter,
three enter,
也就是6,enter,3,enter
times is the same as
six enter three times.
乘,和6乘以3一样
Okay, so six enter three times
is gonna do an automatic enter
好了,6 enter 3 乘 会自动来一个enter
on that three.
在那个3之上
Cuz obviously,
I intend to have six and
显然,在这种情况下,我想让6和
three be multiplied
in that case.
3相乘
So for all of these
operations, I going to say,
对于所有的操作符,我要说的是
if the users in the middle
of typing a number.
如果用户在中间输入一个数字,
Then hit enter for
me, right here.
然后点击enter键.
Okay, so [COUGH] what
do we need to do in
好了,我们需要
this specific case of times?
在乘这里做什么?
Well, really we just want
to set our display value.
我们需要在这里显示计算的结果.
Remember we have our nice
display value down here.
记住,我们有自己的显示值的方法.
And we can do setting
as well as getting.
我们可以进行赋值,也可以进行取值
So I set that display value.
因此,在这里赋值.
Up here.
这里.
Equal to multiplying the top
two things on this stack.
等于将栈顶的两个数相乘
So I can actually remove
something off our stack.
因此,我可以从栈里移除一些元素.
We're representing our
stack as an array.
我们使用一个数组带代表栈结构.
Of course,
they are stacked as an array.
当然了,确实是使用一个数组来表示的栈.
And so a stack is something
you push things on,
栈是一个可以压入元素到栈离,
you pop things off.
可以从栈里弹出元素
And with an array, we're just
gonna add something there at
使用数组的话,只要
the end to push something on,
and
在数组的末尾添加一个元素来模拟元素入栈
that will just remove it
from the end to pop it off.
在数组的末尾移除一个元素来模拟元素出栈
So there's a nice.
这种模拟看起来很酷吧.
All right.
This is an array, right?
好了,这是一个数组,是么?
Operand stacks.
操作符栈.
There's a nice method
called remove last.
有个很好使的方法叫做:移除最后一个元素
And if we option click on
remove last, you'll see here
如果在removelast方法上按住option键,
that it removes an element
from the end of the array.
可以看到说明:从数组的末尾移除一个元素
Now, it does require
a count greater than zero.
需要数组的元素个数大于零.
So if our array were empty
this would crash our program.
如果数组是空的话,移除元素会导致程序崩溃
So let's put a little
protective thing here.
所以,在这里做一些保护性的措施.
If the operand stacks.
如果操作符栈
There's a nice property
here called Count on that.
操作符栈变量有一个属性叫做Count
It is greater or
如果大于或者
equal to two actually because
multiply takes two operand so
等于2,因为乘法需要2个操作数
there better two
things on this stack.
所以至少需要栈中有2个元素
Then we can do this and so
然后,我们可以这样做,
we're gonna multiply that
by and remove the next one.
相乘,然后移除最后一个元素
Okay?
对么?
So here we got-
这样的话,
We're just taking the last two
things off of this stack by
我们从栈中移除最后两个元素,
removing them from
the end of the array and
通过从数组中移除元素
just assigning it
to display value.
赋值给displayValue变量
And we probably also
want to do an enter here,
这里可能需要做一个enter,
because [COUGH] if I go
six enter three times,
如果单击6 enter 3 乘,
well then I want to be able
to say then nine plus and
这样就得到9加
have it add onto
the six times three.
然后加上6乘以3
So we want an automatic
enter here, as well.
这里需要一个自动点击enter,
Okay?
是么?
So, that's pretty much
all we need to do here.
这大概就是我们需要在这里做的了.
Let's go ahead and run this,
see how this works.
继续,运行这个程序,看它是怎么工作的,
And so, six enter, or
three enter, six enter.
6 确认 或者 3 确认 6 确认
Now we've got them
both on the stack.
可以在栈上看到它们
Times and you can see
we put our 18 here.
相乘,然后可以看到结果是18
It also put it back
on the stack and
结果也被放入的栈中,
we can say five times.
比如,5 乘
That put a five
on the stack and
将5放入栈中,
then multiplied them,
took it off.
将它们相乘,从栈中移除,
So that's working nicely.
程序运行的不错啊
[COUGH] Now what about our-
现在,
Other buttons, here.
这里,我们的其他的按钮,
We gonna make those work.
我们要让它们工作.
Let's do that.
让我们完成这个工作.
Now, they do a very
similar thing, here.
它们需要完成十分相似的事情,
So, one temptation would
be to just copy here.
所以,来复制下这部分,
Let's uncomment these out.
打开这部分的注释,
And then just paste it,
repeatedly.
然后粘贴到这里,重复粘贴,
So, put it there.
放到这里.
There, there and then just
changes times in here.
只需要更改这里的乘号.
D note to plus for
example on this one.
这个换成一个加号,
But his is pretty messy code,
look at all this
但是,这样的代码看起来很乱,
incredible amount of
duplicating code, in here.
这里有大量的重复的代码,
We really probably wouldn't
to write our code like this.
我们确实不希望我们的代码写成这样.
People would think we were
terrible programmers I
别人会认为我们是很糟糕的程序员
think if we did that.
如果我们像这样写代码的话.
Really what would be
nice is if we had some,
什么样的代码看起来会不错呢?
could write some
kind of function.
那就是如果我们可以把这些重复的代码写成函数
Maybe we could call it
perform operation or
我们可能会给这个函数起名perfomOperation
something like that.
或者类似意思的名字.
And if the argument
to that function.
至于函数的参数,
Remember that
arguments have names.
注意,函数参数也是又名字的,
Here's the name.
这就是名字.
And then we have the type.
然后是参数类型.
The argument were something
which basically was this
这里的参数就是
little operation in here, or
这里的操作符,
some sort of function that
would do this operation.
这就是完成操作符操作的函数.
So if this could be some
sort of function that
如果可以写成函数的话,
would be cool.
看起来就不错了.
Then, maybe we could.
然后,我们可能会,
I take this code out of here,
put it in here.
将这段代码移动到这里,
Let's call it perform not
pre-form, perform operation.
起码为perform,而不是pre-form
[LAUGH] Put it in here and
放在这里.
instead of doing,
you know, multiply here.
你懂的,这里不是使用乘.
Let's go ahead and we can
do this operation some how.
继续,完成这个操作.
I guess, well maybe operation,
可能是operation函数,
call it like a function
with two arguments here.
像一个带两个参数的函数一样调用.
Okay.
That would be
好了,看起来很不错了.
cool because we'd be sharing,
you know, this check.
因为我们共用了这段代码.
We'd be sharing this enter.
公用了这enter方法
[COUGH] We'd be sharing
the removal of the operator.
共用了removal操作方法.
We'd be sharing
the same display value.
共用了displayValue变量.
We'd be kind of sharing
a lot of code here and
这样,公用了大段的代码,
then up here if we could
just do something like,
在上面,只需要像这样做,
perform operation,
and, somehow, specify,
调用函数,
multiply, as the operation
we wanted to do here.
指定函数参数,
And then we wouldn't need
all this stuff here, right?
这段代码就不需要了,对么?
So this is gonna be cool.
看起来很不错吧?
Now, can we do this?
可以这样做么?
Well, yes,
the answer is we can.
当然了,可以的.
And so, types, functions.
参数类型,函数
Can be types in Swift,
just like any other type.
在Swift里可以当做类型,就像其他的类型一样
So, you know, we have
a double here, oops, double.
这里需要一个double,
That's a type.
就是这个类型,
You can also have
a function type.
也可以有一个函数类型.
So how do you specify
a function type?
那么,怎么指定一个函数类型呢?
Well multiple I or
比如multiple,
whatever function I'm
about to perform here.
或者是任何其他想要执行的函数,
This is a function that takes
two doubles as arguments.
这个函数需要两个double类型的参数
And it returns a double.
函数的返回值类型也是一个double类型
So, I can just say,
I want operation to be
我想要一个函数,
a function that takes two
doubles and returns a double.
带两个double类型参数,返回double类型
I can express that right here.
这就是我要表达的,
This is a type,
the type of this.
这就是参数类型,这种类型.
Argument right here that you
can click on and say yeah
在这里的参数上右键,
that type is double takes two
doubles and returns a double.
可以看到信息:2个double类型的参数,一个double类型返回值.
So, just simple as that.
就是这么简单.
So all we need now
is a function here
我们所知道的,这里是一个函数,
called multiply that
takes two doubles and
函数名multiply,带2个参数,
returns a double and
does multiplication.
返回double类型,完成乘法操作.
So we could go down here and
say okay multiply and
好了,看下面的乘,
you'll have op1 which
is double and op2.
有一个参数,double类型,第二个参数,
[COUGH] A double and
it returned the double.
double类型,返回一个double类型.
And it's just return
one times out two.
这个函数返回参数1乘以参数2
Okay?
对么?
And that worked great.
看来起不错哟!
Back out again so we can
see if this actually works.
回到上面,看它是否真的可以正常运行.
But there's no arrows here.
没有任何错误.
Right?
It seems to work.
对么?看起来可行.
Multiply seems to be
a function to take the $2 and
turns it double.
And that's what this
argument here is and
这里的这个参数,
I'm passing it along.
将它传入
It should all work so
let's give it a try.
应该是可行的,那么试一下吧.
So here we go as
it takes enter.
点下enter
54 times and
sure enough it's working it.
54乘以,好了,没问题.
It's doing that
multiplication.
完成了乘法操作.
Works great and so what about
all of our other cases here?
做的不错,其他的case语句呢?
Well we would just
need to take this same.
只需要也像这样做.
Piece of code right here and
put it for all of them.
所有的case语句,这里一段代码,
And of course we need a divide
method, so we have to
当然了,我们需要除法函数,
come down here, and copy and
paste that, and make divide.
来到下面,复制,粘贴,起名divide
Oh wait a second,
稍等,
this is starting to be just
as bad as I had before.
看起来又像之前的一样,很糟糕了.
Having to make all these
extra functions, multiply and
需要这些额外的函数,乘法,
divide and all that.
触发,等等.
Well [COUGH] it
turns out it's so
事情上,
common to pass functions as
arguments in Swift, that it
字啊Swift中,把函数作为参数传递是很常见的.
allows you to put a function
like multiply right in
允许你传递一个,比如multiply,的函数,
here without having to create
a separate function like this.
不需要再创建一个函数
And all you do is
you just pick it up.
需要做的是,选中,
So I'm just going to cut
that from down here and
从这里剪切
I'm going to paste
it right in here.
粘贴到这里来
The only thing you have to
change syntactically when you
唯一需要做语法上的改变的是,
do that is this curly brace,
okay.
这里是一个大括号.
Instead of being after
the declaration of
而不是之前在声明
the arguments in the return
value, it needs to be before.
函数,返回值之后.
So, you move the curly
brace before.
把大括号放到前面.
And then where
the curly brace was,
之前这里是小括号.
you gonna put in, the word in.
这里添加一个单词in
And so that allows us to just.
允许我们稍微调整下.
Come and do that again to
eliminate some of our errors.
现在把这些错误解决了,
And we can get rid of
function multiply down here.
移除这里的mutiply
So that allows me to just put
that multiplier right in here.
把乘法放在这里.
Right in line.
就是这里.
Write as the argument
to this function.
给这个函数写一个参数.
And this things kind of wacky.
看起来略古怪.
For those of you
who don't know it,
对于一些不了解的人来讲,
user programming languages
that allow this kind
编程语言中,
of thing to happen
are called closures.
这种情况称之为闭包.
It basically allows you to put
a function right in there.
允许在这里放一个函数.
And this, okay here, looks
okay, I mean we can certainly
好了,这看起来还不错.
you know, now we can copy and
paste this and put it here.
下面又是复制,粘贴,放着
You know, here and
放这里
change this and
put it here and change this.
改了这个,放在这里,改了这个,
But it can even be
better than this.
但是,我们可以进一步改进.
So we know that Swift
is really good at
我们知道Swift很擅长的
something called
type inference.
一个特性称为类型引用.
Where I can kinda
figure out the type,
从类型引用可以看出是什么类型,
of something,
from the context.
结合上下文来看.
And you can do
the same thing here.
这里也可以这么做.
Because its looking
at perform operation.
看下这里的performOperation
It knows you're calling
perform operation.
它知道你在调用performOperation
It knows this argument is
a function that takes two
它知道这个函数的参数,
doubles and returns a double.
2个double类型,一个double类型的返回值.
So you really don't have to
specify all the types in here.
所以,这里不需要明确的指定类型,
Cuz it knows all of this.
因为它知道这些事情.
So you can actually get rid of
all these type decorations,
所以,可以删除这些类型声明.
right here, even the return.
甚至是返回值类型也可以省去.
And, again,
seeing no warnings, no errors.
可以看到,没有任何警告,错误.
It knows that this has
to be a double, and
它知道这个参数是double,
this has to be a double.
这个参数也是dobule类型.
Because it knows you're
calling perform operation.
因为它知道你需要调用的函数.
So it knows the argument
to that is like that.
就像这样,它知道函数的参数.
Okay, and you can even make
this look a little nicer.
好了,可以进行进一步的改进.
We can move this all
up onto one line.
把这些上移一行.
Really nice for
readability here.
看来起更具有可读性.
But, we can actually do
even better than this,
事实上,我们可以做的更好.
because Swift knows that
perform operations argument
因为Swift知道这个函数
returns something, you don't
need this return key if your
返回一个值,所以你不需要return
whole is just an expression
like this return key word.
如果所有的代码只有一个返回语句.
You don;t need that key word
because it knows this is
不需要return这个关键字了,
going to return something so
因为程序知道你要返回什么.
this is just an expression
it's going to return it.
这样只返回一个表达式就可以了.
But it's even better than
that because a swift does
更好的做法是,
not force you to name
these two arguments.
swift不强制你给这两个参数命名.
If you don;t name them it
will use the names Dar0.
如果不手动命名的话,程序自动给参数起码$0
Dollar 1, and
$1,
if you have more arguments,
dollar 2, dollar 3, dollar 4.
如果有更多的参数,会命名为$2,$3,$4.
So you don't even need this.
所以,这也不要了.
Okay?
对么?
So this is a function
right here.
这里是一个函数.
It takes two doubles,
dollar 0 and dollar 1, and
这个函数有两个double类型参数,$0,$1
returns a double.
返回一个double类型的值.
Now Swift knows that they're
doubles because it knows that
Swift知道它们是double类型.
you're passing them to
perform an operation.
因为你将它们传递给了这个函数.
If you were passing this to
some other, a function that
如果把它们传递给其他的函数,
took different kind of
function as an argument, then,
比如有不同类型的参数,
you know, these types might be
different but in this case it
这些类型可能和上面不同.
knows that's what it is and
it knows that it returns once
但是Swift知道该使用什么类型
it knows it's going to return
what this calculation is.
这里就是这样的.
All right.
好了.
Now one more cool syntactic
thing you can do is if you
更酷的事情是,
have a function like
performOperation, and
如果有一个performOperation这样的函数,
it has an argument which is a
function like operation here,
有个像operation这样的参数,
if this argument is
the last argument, okay, so
如果是最后一个参数,
if I had other arguments
before it, and
在之前又别的参数,
this was the argument, then
you can move the function.
这是参数,可以移动这个函数的位置
Outside the parentheses,
so other arguments,
移动到括号外,参数也是.
if there were other arguments
before, they would go in here.
如果又其他类型的参数,可以放在这里.
But this last argument,
但是这个最后的一个参数.
which is this operation, gets
to go outside the parentheses.
这个函数,需要放在括号外.
And if there are no other
arguments, if this is
如果没有其他的参数,
the only argument, you can
actually get rid of that.
如果只有一个参数,可以删除它.
Okay.
好了.
So, we're cutting down
to incredibly concise
因此,我们把程序变得很简洁了
language here and we can
do this exact same deal,
可以再这样做.
of course with these
other form operations.
其他的操作也可以这样做.
We just need to change the.
只需要改这里.
Nothing here.
这里不需要改.
This one, we be a little
careful with the order of
这里,需要注意参数的顺序,
operations here,
we wanna do this because we
我们会这么做,
click the thing that we're
dividing by on the stack last.
除以栈中的最后一个元素.
And that's the first thing
that comes off the stack.
栈中最先离开的元素
And same thing here actually,
这里也要注意,
the subtraction
minus dollar here.
减法,减号,$,
Okay, so, this is our
entire operate, and
好了,这就是我们的全部操作.
you can see that it's
incredibly concise.
你可以看到,这相当的简洁.
Very readable.
很高的可读性.
TImes is clearly
doing this function.
这里改成乘法.
And very extensible.
也有很高的可扩展性
If you wanna add
more functions,
如果需要添加更多的操作,
we just one liners here,
只需要这里添加一行代码.
but more these [COUGH] binary
functions that have two So,
这里我们就只有这么多.
let's go ahead and make
sure these are all working.
继续,确保我们程序运行问题.
All right.
好的.
So, 6 enter 5 times,
that's 30, that's good.
6乘以5,结果是30,看起来不错.
How about 47 plus 77,
excellent.
47加上77,不错.
How about 2 divide.
2除以
38.5.
38.5
[INAUDIBLE] number there.
这个数,三十八点五.
Working, you can see the stack
doing all the right things.
正常,可以看到做的还错.
Okay?
Make sense?
对么?正确的吧?
Now, I'm going to do
one more thing, here.
现在,还需要做一个事情.
Which is to add
another operation,
就是添加另外的一个操作符.
this is going to be a slightly
different operation.
稍有不同的一个操作.
So, I'm going to copy and
复制一下,
paste these operation
buttons here.
粘贴到这里.
Again, I'm going to make sure
they are lined up really
确保真正的对齐了.
nice with as many of these
blue lines as I can get.
使用蓝色的线来对齐.
I'm actually going to
leave these buttons here.
把按钮放在这.
Because you're going to need
them for your homework.
But we gonna change this
button right down here to be
a different operator.
Which is going to be,
square root.
Which is right here,
square root operator.
All right?
And, so, I'm going to go back
her to do square root, and
it's just another case, right.
Case square root.
And, maybe I should just
be able to use the same
mechanism, right?
Let's see if that works.
Place that in there.
And instead of this bracket
here, let's use the built in
function in Swift to do
square root called sqrt.
And a dollar there.
Looks good.
And then we're ready to go.
Let's just work, call it,
what's going on here.
They have some sort of error,
what's the problem.
I don't understand.
Let's take a look at this.
Now this error is a little
hard to understand but
basically what it's saying
is that you're calling
performOperation here with an
argument which is a function,
it only takes on argument.
Goes Swift looks here and
it's used that it's only
using a dollar zero so
this is a one argument
function this whole
curly brace thing is a
function that is one argument.
Well four operation
takes a function that
has two arguments.
So that's a mismatch
that doesn't work.
So how can we fix this.
Well actually believe it or
not we can just make a copy of
form operation of another
method, same name.
This one we are gonna
have different arguments.
It's gonna have a,
an argument which is
a function that only takes one
double and returns a double.
And then inside here,
obviously we don't need to
pull two things off the stack,
just one.
And obviously we only need to
check to make sure there
is one thing on the stack.
And look,
all error warnings gone, okay?
So it automatically
figured out that this
performer operation
must be this one,
because this is a function
that only has one argument.
And so it matched it up
with this version of it.
So in Swift, you can have
functions with the same name.
As long as they have
different arguments.
And that Swift will
automatically pick
the right one, if it can.
There are sometimes
when it's just like,
I can't really tell
which one you mean.
And it will certainly
complain, in that case.
But most of the type it's
gonna be on [INAUDIBLE] from
the types involved,
what's going on.
So, just gonna run this
one again real quick.
[INAUDIBLE] 36 square root.
Looks like it's working,
9 times square root.
Excellent.
Okay.
All right.
So,
the last thing I'm going
to do here is work on
the layout of these buttons.
So that's all I'm gonna do for
the code.
You can see that we
really didn't have to
write that much code.
To make this work and
we got to do a lot of
stuff in our UI here.
So, let's go ahead and make it
so these buttons spread out.
Cuz right now you see all this
space is wasted right here.
And on an iPhone
in portrait mode.
Whole bottom space is wasted.
And an iPhone on
landscape mode,
this whole size can be wasted.
So I really want these
buttons much bigger, and
stretching out.
Now, when you do something
like that, you have to think
a little bit of kind of what
your strategy is gonna be.
You can't just kinda root
four start, you know,
control drag it
between things.
And trying to set up
the horizontal spacing,
and maybe line up the, make
the equal width and height.
Oh my gosh, you'd be control
dragging all day long,
by doing that.
So I'm not going to use
control drag to do this.
I'm going to use these buttons
down here which will kind of
bulk out a layout buttons.
Let's go ahead and
use the whole screen here.
Document outline.
So what is going
to be my strategy?
Well, my strategy is I'm going
to make a perfect grid here.
So, I almost have one, except
for there's one missing here.
So I'm actually going to take
a button, copy and paste it.
Okay, just kind of be
a dummy button here actually.
With no title.
I'm going to right click on it
also because I don't want it
sending appendage or
anything else, So
its not going to
send any messages.
But it's just a dummy,
so I'm kind of using.
A little bit of brains
over brawn here to do
this perfect grid.
Now if I have this perfect
grid, then if I had a rule
where all these buttons had to
be the same size, and they all
had the same spacing between
their neighbors, not just.
Between each other but the
same spacing to this edge and
the same spacing
to this top edge.
Okay, if I had a rule like
that then they would get
big and of course the spacing
is facing from this edge
to edge and
this edge to this edge.
If it was all the exactly the
same, which I'll make it be
whatever this is, whatever the
dash for the lines gave me.
If that was the same then they
would all have to spread out.
Okay, they'd get bigger but
they'd all stay the same
size because I'm going to
make a rule that they
have to be the same size.
But they would move
out to this edge so
that this nearest neighbor
would be the same, you know,
this distance would be
the same as this distance.
So that's my strategy,
I'm going to try to do that.
Now to make that work,
all these buttons need to know
who their nearest neighbor is.
Well, these all know their
nearest neighbor here,
the other buttons, because
I made sure I used dashed,
blue lines when I
dragged them in there.
So, that's what kind of
teaches them their
nearest neighbor.
And I'm also going to make
sure that the entire grid
knows that the left edge and
just under the label there,
our nearest neighbor.
So now it knows on the top,
the nearest neighbor
is the label, and
on the left is this edge.
And it's going to
pick this edge as
the nearest neighbor for these
buttons and the bottom edge,
cuz that's all there is and
nothing else out here
that's gonna become,
that's the only neighbor there
is, it's gonna pick those.
So now that I've
used my dash for
the lines it makes
this all quite easy.
Now, if you don't use
the dash for the lines, or
if you make some mistakes
then it's not going to work.
This strategy won't work and
I've made doing this part of
this demonstration
be extra credit.
And so if you can't get it,
don't worry about it too much,
just keep all your buttons in
the upper left corner here
and that's fine.
But if you want to give
this a try, the key is to
use the dash lines to
make the perfect grid.
Make sure that you set
the nearest neighbors here by
dragging the whole grid to
make blue lines appear on
the sides.
And then, we are going to
set these rules in bulk and
we do that with these
buttons down here.
So there's this button right
here the left most button and
it let's you set things like
lining up leading edges or
the tops or the centers.
And you could imagine there
might be a way to do this by
doing that but I am not
going to use that strategy.
My strategy is just make
them the same size and
make the space in between
them, be the same.
But, I bet there's
probably a way to do it by
lining up their centers, or
something like that, too.
So I'm not going
to use this one.
The next one over,
right here, is the one that
has the things I want.
And so you can see
that it'll ask you to
make all the buttons
equal widths and heights.
Okay, not width and
height, that fixes them
at a certain width and
height, this means that there,
they can be any width and
height they want, but they all
have to be the same width and
height all these buttons.
Of course I had these all
selected by the way, if you
don't have them selected
it doesn't make any sense.
And then up here, you can
see there is spacing to
nearest neighbor, so this
is where I am going to set
that spacing between all
these, to be the same.
And you can see that
it's put eight here.
That's because when I
did the the dash lines
to the top eight seems to be
kind of a standard number of
points between elements.
These are all multiple because
some of these buttons,
their nearest neighbor is
way over here and it's huge.
All right.
The bottom or their right.
But all these buttons,
the thing on top,
whether it's another button or
whether it's this label,
all of them happen to be this
eight points right here.
So I want all of
these to be eight.
So I'm just going to turn this
bar on right here, which says,
yes please enforce, and
make the rule that all of
these are 8 points from their
nearest neighbor to the top.
And also, 8 to the left,
8 to the right, and
8 to the bottom.
Really wanna make sure
these beams are on,
if these beams are off,
even if there's a number here,
then it's not gonna
add this rule.
So we wanted to add this rule.
So this adds up to
87 different rules.
All these equal widths and
heights and all these So
if you don't have 87 in here,
if it says a hundred and
something,
probably you don't have
everything lined up right.
It only takes 87 constraints
to express all these rules.
All right.
Now, when I click this
Add 87 Constraints it's
going to add these rules
to all these buttons, and
watch what happens.
So, I get all kinds of,
first these blue lines
are showing me the rules.
'Kay?
A lot them are saying here
that things are equal
widths and heights.
So these are what
equals rules means.
But there's also tiny little
I beams right up here.
That are showing this basing
to nearest neighbor, and
also like there's a yellow,
yellow here.
This yellow,
remember, means yeah,
there's constraints on these,
but they're not actually where
they're supposed to be
based on those rules.
So we really want to move
them all to be in their
proper spaces based
on these rules.
That's what these dashed
yellow lines mean.
So we can do the same
thing to do that,
that we did at the beginning
with the label on the top
which is go to our
document outline here,
in the lower left corner.
Okay these are document
outline when we last saw it,
it only had this
one label in there.
Now we got all these
buttons added.
And you can see
they're all selected.
All selected here as well.
And, we've got this little
yellow thing up here.
Now, if this is red, okay,
if you do all this and
this is red, well that means
that you've got not just
warnings that your constraints
aren't in the right place, but
you've got errors, usually
conflicting constraints,
where you've asked
auto layout to
enforce two rules that
conflict with each other.
So if you get to that red,
this is not going to work.
So, you'll want to start over,
and
I'll show you in a minute how
you can start over if things,
or not going your way, but
if it's yellow that just means
things were in
the wrong place.
So no problem,
we click the yellow.
Here's all the things that
were in the wrong place.
This is all the buttons,
you can see they highlight
as I mouse over them.
And you can really pick on
any one of them to fix this
because there's a nice little
switch here called apply to
all views and containers.
You don't have to
click on each one and
have it to frame update
to the proper thing.
You can just click quite
obvious in container and it's
going to move the frame of all
the buttons top fix the fact
that they're in the wrong
place based on their rules.
So let's try that.
I'm gonna hit this button
here, Fix Misplacement.
And it moved them all.
There's no more yellow.
There's no auto layout issues.
Okay.
All looks good here.
We can close our
document outline.
We zoom out, we can see,
wow, it spread them all out.
Okay?
Because,
maybe it's obeying
those rules I gave it.
Okay?
So let's now run this on
some devices here and
see what this looks like.
So turn off on an iPhone 6,
which is a pretty tall device.
It's made, you know,
kind of tall and thin.
So if this still
works fine enter.
69874 times 5 divide maybe
square root something like
that, it all seems
to be working.
Now, not only is it working
here in this portrait mode,
tall and thin.
But if we go over here to this
we can rotate the device.
Okay, so
I'm going to rotate left and
right and use the command
keys to do this.
And we rotate it right and
you see it
may the buttons spread out
to this new location and
we can rotate back using
the command keys here.
And it looks good in
either orientation.
And in fact, it can look good
on other devices as well.
So let's go over here and
instead of doing iPhone 6,
let's try it on an iPhone 4S.
Okay so,
gonna switch the simulation
here, let's run that.
Now the iPhone 4s, you can
see is a little shorter,
it's not quite as tall.
A little lower resolution,
obviously.
But it relayed out the buttons
to look good in that case too.
9 times 9, divided by 8,
square root, et cetera.
And same thing here
we can rotate and
look at this one as well.
Okay.
All righty.
So the last thing I just want
to talk about briefly is if
you try this extra credit and
it doesn't work for you.
Get all messed up, you can
kind of start over by clicking
on this and using the third
button over here on the right.
And this allows you to
reset your constraints and
you can see the top section
here is the selected views.
I don't have any
selected here so
this wouldn't do
anything right now.
But the bottom is all
views in container and
I kinda recommend going
down here to all views
container and clearing
the constraints entirely.
Reset to suggested
constraints and try and
make some sense of your dashed
lines but if it's not working,
you're probably, you're
dashed lines are off anyway.
So you can just go here and
Clear Constraints,
that'll clear them all.
Now that's gonna clear
not just your buttons but
also it's gonna
clear your labels.
So you'll have to reposition
your label with blue lines and
use control drag to say
your top space, and, and
all that stuff, you know?
If your buttons are really
huge, they got really huge,
but they're not in the right
place, you can actually change
the size of all your buttons
in the utilities window.
You can go to the size
inspector right here,
that's this one, you can
actually type in the width and
the height you want
the buttons to be, make them
smaller again, which,
you know, maybe 64 by 64.
That might make them easier to
re-drag them into position so
the blue lines are working.
And don't forget the very
important blue line dragging,
which is you want to take
the whole grid and drag it,
so that it's sitting
underneath your label.
If you have problems dragging
the whole grid underneath your
label, sometimes it's
a good idea, clear all
your constraints, kind of move
your buttons out of the way,
just kind of move them down
to the bottom here and then
just for your label, do reset
to suggest your constraint.
This top one selected view
Rest Suggestion Constraints
cuz that will work for
the label if you move it
into position as long as
the buttons aren't too close
and it thinks that, you know.
Those buttons are near
neighbors or something.
And sometimes resetting it to
suggest the constraints will
make it so that, that bottom
edge of your UI label will
be attainable when you drag
your buttons into position.
But again, not to
worry too much about
this auto layout stuff.
It's extra credit
in assignment one.
It's not going to be extra
credit in assignment two,
so you're eventually
going to have to do it.
I'm going to be giving a big
lecture on this in a couple of
weeks, on auto layout.
I've really just shown you
just kind of what it can do,
I haven't really
taught you how to do
auto layout in particular.
Auto layout is very important
because we work in this
square area and
we want our UIs to work on all
kinds of different devices.
That's why we're
starting off in the very
start with some
experience with it.
All right.
So that is it.
Now, later today,
I'm gonna, in this lecture,
I'm gonna give you a talk
about this design paradigm
called model-view-controller,
and we actually designed our
calculator kind of poorly,
because all of
this code here is really
nothing to do with UI.
This is all calculator brain,
calculator engine code.
And this really wants to
meet a different object and
that's what NBC is all about.
And so I'll give a little
talk about NBC later today.
And then on Monday, we're
going to fix our calculator
to obey MVC and be a proper
citizen in the iOS world,
where all apps need to obey
model V controller paradigm.
>> So let's try and
understand for, I mean half of
you said that you already
know MVC or you've seen it
somewhere else so, this is
going to be mostly review.
But the other half of you,
this will hopefully give you
an idea of what
MVC is all about.
So MVC is basically
a mechanism where we divide up
all the objects in our
application into one of
these three camps.
Okay?
So, the three camps.
On the left there
you see the model.
So, the model camp is gonna be
all the objects that are what
your application does.
So, for our calculator its,
it calculates.
Okay, that's what it does.
So, all the parts what we're
doing perform operation, and
all that stuff, that's all
kind of calculator stuff.
That should be in a calculator
object somewhere else,
it shouldn't be in
our controller.
And then the second camp is
the controller, the controller
controls how the model
is presented on screen.
And the view is the minions,
the classes that
the controller is going
to use are kind of
like the the building blocks,
the Lincoln Logs,
I know maybe that's
before all of your time.
But, you know, these things
we're gong to do to build our
UI, we're going to
use in the view.
So the stuff that's in the
view is pretty generic, okay,
generic UI elements.
The stuff in the controller
is very specific to
how your UI works.
And the stuff in the model
is completely independent of
how your UI works.
Okay?
So doing MVC right is about
knowing where things go but
also about how to communicate
between these three camps.
And so we can try and
summarize how
the communication works
between these camps, and
I've used road markings, you
see the double yellow line and
then the dashed white line.
So that's like you're
driving in your car.
Try to use them as an image
for how this communication
happens, where it's allowed,
where it's not allowed.
So let's talk about
the Controller talking to
the Model.
Going from that side of the
road over to the Model side is
a dashed white line,
in other words,
you can head right
across there.
You probably want to
look before you go, but
you can go right across, okay?
The controller has to know
everything about the model,
and it has to have complete
ability to talk to
the model, use its public
API as much as it wants
because the controller's job
is to present the model to
the user using its
view as its minions.
So it has to have this access.
That full, unrestricted access
the controller has talking to
the model.
This is a one way arrow.
Control, or
one way arrow, from
the controller to the model.
And similarly, from
the controller to the view,
is also unlimited
communication,
because the controller
is responsible for
talking using
it's own minions.
The view is, the controller's
new meaning is
to lay out the user interface
and all that stuff.
So, the controller can
do anything it wants.
I put that little green word,
outlet,
up there because when we have
a property of a controller
that points into the view,
we call it an outlet, okay?
And you're gonna see that
in the demo on Wednesday.
I'm gonna say, oh let's create
an outlet from our controller
to our view so
our controller can talk
to it's view, all right?
What about this communication?
Model to view?
Never.
And why is that?
100% obvious, the model is
completely UI independent.
So, there's absolutely
no way it could talk to
a viewer object or
anyone in that camp.
Because the view objects
are fundamentally UI objects.
They're kind of generic, but
they're still
fundamentally UI objects.
Similarly, since the view
objects are kind of generic,
they can't be talking
to any specific model.
They need a controller
to interpret a model
for them, okay?
So there's never any
communication this way.
That's why it's
a double yellow line.
That's why these
lines are red.
That's why there's fire, okay?
Never go across that line,
ever.
What about the view talking
back to the controller?
You got these generic view
objects, like buttons.
Can they talk to
the controller?
Well, yes, they can.
But, they have to be careful
because the view objects
are generic.
So they can't really know
much about the controller.
So, they can only communicate
back to the controller
in a blind way where they
don't know the class of
the thing they're talking to,
and in a structured way.
A way where we all agree we're
gonna communicate this way
between the view and
the controller.
So, whats an example
of a structured way?
Well one is called
target action.
So, the controller basically
drops a target on itself, and
then it hands out an action,
which is like an arrow,
to the view and
says to the view,
okay, when you do what you do,
like you're a button and
someone touches you or
your a slider and
someone moves you,
send me that action.
Okay?
So, in this way,
the generic button or
slider is communicating
back to the controller.
It has no idea that it's
a card game controller or
a space game controller.
It doesn't know what
kind of controller it is.
All it knows is that when
something happens in itself,
boom, it sends a message
to the target.
So that's a blind, simple,
structured way for
the view to communicate
with the controller.
Okay?
But what about more
complicated ways?
Sometimes the view, things
are happening in the view
that are somewhat complicated,
and
the controller needs to be
informed of what's going on,
synchronizing what's
happening.
And one way to think about
this is these words I
put up here, will,
should and did.
When the view is kind of like,
let's say I am in
the scroll view and
I am scrolling around, and
I want to let the controller
somebody know that
the user just did scroll.
Okay?
Or
the user puts down the touch
and is about to scroll, I want
to let the controller know the
user will be scrolling, okay?
Or, the user puts
the touch down and
the scroll viewer
wants to know,
should I allow the user to
scroll here, is that allowed?
All those things, the scroll
view itself might not
have enough logic to know
the answer to those questions.
So what it does is,
it delegates the authority to
answer those questions
to some other object.
Now, it doesn't know
the class of that object.
All it knows is that
other object can
answer these questions, will,
should, did, this, that, or
the other thing like,
should allow scrolling.
Did scroll to point.
Things like that.
So those are the kind of
methods you are going to see
in these delicate protocols.
Now, I know this here is 1,
6 a and b,
do not teach protocols.
How many people know what
the word protocol means an
object during a programming?
I can see very few of you.
So, I will be teaching that.
A protocol is just a blind way
to talk to another object.
When I teach it,
you're gonna be like oh,
yeah, I know what that is.
So we can really call it
protocol or whatever.
But that's how we do
delegation, okay,
this blind communication.
Also another
important thing is
that views should not own the
data that they're displaying.
They should not own it.
In other words, it shouldn't
be a property inside of them,
where that's the truth
of that data.
And the easiest example for
this is, all the songs in
your iPod, on your iPhone or
your iPad, right?
You might have 10,000
songs in there.
So, if you have some kind
of generic list view in
your view, you can't transfer
all 10,000 songs to its
instance variables, and
expect it to hold 10,000 songs
so it can list through it.
A, that would be inefficient,
and
B that information, those
10,000 songs belongs where?
In the model.
Okay, because your song
database is a model.
It has nothing to do with UI.
It's just a list of songs and
artists and albums and
all that, it's in the model.
Some controller has to
look at that database and
tell a view how to
display all those songs.
Okay?
So, we need that communication
to happen here and the view is
displaying some sort of list,
and you're touching down and
you're flicking on the list
and trying to see more songs,
how does that
communication happen?
And the answer is, we have
another special kind of
delegate, which we
call a data source.
Now the data source doesn't
do the will did should.
It's gonna be asking
questions like count,
like how many songs are there?
And the controller
looks in the model,
10,000 response to the view.
There's 10,000.
The view
makes space internally for
10,000 things.
It doesn't know what they are.
Moves the scroll bar
indicator a little bit so
that you know where it is.
And then you start scrolling,
flipping through it, and
it starts sending the message
to the controller,
give me the data at
line 150 next 10 items.
You see what I mean?
And then you flick
down some more.
Now it's saying 250,
10 more items.
And so the control is going
back to the model and
saying give me more,
give me more data.
And it's providing it to
the view in this blind way.
So to see how the view is
getting data from the model
through the controller in this
kind of blind structured way.
Okay?
That makes sense to everybody?
So data source is just
a kind of delegate,
it's a specific kind of
delegate for getting data.
So you're gonna see that there
are classes in iOS that have
a data source, and they
usually also have a delegate.
Most sophisticated classes in
iOS have a delegate, the will,
did, should, kind of things.
Some of them have
a data source,
it depends on whether they are
showing a lot of data or not.
Now simple data, like if I had
a view, if I invented a view
一些简单的数据，比如我给纸牌游戏
for my card game called
playing card view and
创建了一个叫playing card view的视图
it just has a suit and a rank.
它仅有花色和点数两点属性。
Okay, we're not going to
do count data app for
我们不会为了花色和点数
just suit and rank.
进行计算。
We are going to set
those properties.
我们会把它们设置成属性。
And so the view then would
have that data set in it but
所以view里会有设置好的数据，但是
it wouldn't be owning it.
它不会拥有这些数据。
Right?
The model would still be
model仍然会是花色和点数的
owning the suit and
拥有者，
rank, the view is just getting
that data to present it.
view仅仅是为了显示而获取那些数据。
'Kay.
So simple data,
所以对于简单的数据，
we might transfer to
the view but it's merely for
我们会把它传送到view里，但是
it to display it.
只是给view来显示。
Okay.
This all adds up to
the controller's job being to
所以controller的工作就是
interpret and format
the model's data for the view.
给view解释并格式化这些model提供的数据。
That's the controller's job.
这就是controller的工作。
And when we do our demo,
在我们做deomo的时候，
I'm going to be marking like,
oh see I'm writing this code.
我会在写代码的时候提示大家，
This is to make the controller
perform its job,
这段代码是为了让controller执行它的工作，
which is to take
the model data and
也就是从model中取出数据然后
using its view minion
to put it on screen.
运用到view中去，然后显示到屏幕上。
Okay?
That's what
这就是
the controller does.
controller做的事情。
What about this communication?
那关于通信呢？
Can the model talk
to the controller?
model可以和controller通信吗？
Again, obviously that's
verboten because model knows
同样的，显然是不可以。因为model对于UI
nothing about UI, so
一无所知，所以
it couldn't possibly talk to a
UI object like the controller.
它不可能同像controller一样的UI对象进行通信。
But sometimes things
change in the model, and
但是有些时候，model中的数据变了，
the controller needs to
know about it, okay?
controller需要只要这个变化，OK?
Data changes,
a database changes or
数据改变了，数据库改变了，或者
the model is some
network database, and
model是网络数据库，
somebody changes something on
the network and it changes.
某人在网络上修改了数据，数据改变了。
And the controller
needs to find out.
controller需要了解这些。
So, how do we do
that communication?
所以，我们怎样做这种通信呢？
We do that using kind of
a radio station model.
这可以通过一种电台的模型来理解
Okay?
So, the model, a radio station
concept, the model will use
所以，model是一种电台的概念，
this concept to essentially
broadcast information to
model将会利用这一 概念，把信息广播给
anyone who's interested.
感兴趣的任何人。
Okay?
And the mechanisms for
doing this in iOS are called
在iOS中为了解决这种问题而使用的技术我们叫做
Notification and Key Value
Observing, KVO we call it.
Notification和KVO。
And so, the model can
just say, oh, anytime
所以，model可以说，
something changes in my model
I'm just gonna broadcast on
我当中的任何东西发生了变化，我会通过我的电台
my radio station, and then the
controller simply tunes into
广播一下，随后，controller
that radio station, and he can
find out things are changing.
会接收到来自电台的信息，它会发现数据在变化
And when he finds out
something changes,
发现数据变化以后，
it's gonna communicate via its
green arrow to the model and
它就会通过它的绿剪头同model进行通信，
say, okay, give me
that data that changed.
给我那个改变过的数据。
Right?
That make sense?
能听懂吗？
So, towards the end of
the quarter we'll start seeing
所以在课程快要结束的时候，我们将会学习
a little how to do
notification to find out, for
如何利用通知得知
example, if the data
in a database changes.
数据库中的数据发生了改变。
We'll get a notification,
the UI can then, you know,
我们将会获取这个通知，UI中的controller
controller can then go talk
to the model to get the info.
随后可以同model通信来获取信息。
Okay?
Some people have asked,
有些人会问，
can a view tune into
the radio station?
view可以接收广播吗？
They probably could, but
它们也许可以，但是
you probably wouldn't
want to do that.
你最好不要这样做。
That would probably be
a violation of MVC.
这可能违背了MVC的原则。
All right.
好的。
So we do this.
我们这样做，
We have all this nice
communication and
我们有这些很好的通信和
all these rules,
所有的这些规则。
and we can imagine building
something simple using this.
我们可以利用这些来制作一些小的应用。
But what if we wanna build
a big complicated app?
但是如果我们想要制作一个巨大复杂的应用呢？
An app that has multiple
screens on our iPhone, or
一个在iPhone或iPad上运行，有多个屏幕，
an iPad, it's got three or
在屏幕上有三个或四个不同的区域，
four different areas on screen
where things are happening.
都发生着事情。
How do we do that?
我们该怎么做？
Well, we're
essentially going to
我们
combine multiple MVCs, okay?
会结合多个MVC
Because an MVC can use as part
of its view, another MVC.
因为一个MVC可以将另一个MVC当做视图的一部分。
Okay?
So an MVC,
an entire MVC can be one of
所以一个完整的MVC可以被一个稍大些的
the minions of
some bigger MVC.
MVC当做仆人使用。
'Kay?
And by doing that and
cascading it down,
我们可以一层一层地这样堆叠，
we can build more and
more complicated applications.
就可以制作出越来越复杂的应用。
So, an example of this is, you
might have your calendar app,
例如，你可能有一个日历应用，
and it's showing you
the entire year.
它展示给你一整年的信息。
And you click on a month, and
now it shows you a month view.
随后你点击了一个月份，于是它展示给你月视图。
Well, a month view looks a lot
different than a year view.
月视图看起来和年视图就不太一样了。
A month view just has all
the days and maybe some circle
一个月视图只含有所有的日期，也许在日期上
that tells you where you have
an appointment on a day.
会有一些通知你在某天会有任务的圈圈。
And then when you
click on a day, and
随后，你点击了一天，然后你
now you get a day view, okay?
获得了一个日视图
And the day is showing you
the hours and what all
日视图会显示小时信息和这天你的所有
your appointments are, and you
click on the Appointment now
任务，随后你点击了任务，
you get an appointment view
and it showing the detail of
你会获得任务视图，它会显示任务的细节，
where you're going and
when it is et cetera, okay?
将要去哪，何时动身还有其它一些东西
Well, each of those views,
year view, month view, the day
这些view中的每一个，年视图，月视图，日视图，
view, and the appointment
view are their own MVCs.
任务视图，都有他们自己的MVC。
Okay?
But you can see how
the last three, okay,
但是你可以发现，最后三个view,
are used as essentially a
minion of the top level view,
都被最顶层的年视图为了展示更多的细节
year view,
to show more detail, okay?
而被当做仆人使用。
So the year view,
you click on a month,
所以在年视图里，你点击了一个月份，
it's going to use the month
view MVC to show more detail.
它会利用月份视图的MVC来展现更多细节。
So it's part of its view,
okay?
所以它是它视图的一部分，
So, you see this also
in iOS with tab bar
所以你也在带有便签控制栏的iOS应用
controllers, right?
中见过这些吧
You have the tab bar at
the bottom, I have four or
在底部有一个标签栏，有四个或五个
five things you can choose.
项可以供你选择。
Well there's some MVC at the
top whose has four pointers to
在上面有一个MVC，它指向四个仆人，
four minions, which are the
four MVCs that are each going
也就是将要出现在标签栏中的MVC，
to appear in a tab bar, okay?
We'll be doing that for
我们将会做一个这方面的例子，
example, in assignment
number two or
在第二次或第三次作业，我们会
three where we'll be
making a tab bar and
制作一个标签栏，
you're gonna have to do
multiple MVCs, okay?
你们将会学习如何使用多个MVC
So, that basically results
in a picture looks kinda
所以使用多个MVC的效果看起来就像
like this.
这张图片一样。
All right?
Where you got this MVC, and
在你看到的这个MVC里，
you see the purple one that's
like underneath the word
找到'together'下面的那个
together there, and
紫色的，
it points to three other MVCs
outside of its view thing.
它从view指向了另外三个MVC，
Okay?
That's how we're
going to build it, so
这就是我们创建标签栏控制器的方式，
that might be a tab
bar control and
这些可能就是它的
those might be the three tabs.
三个标签。
Okay, and
each one is its own little MVC
并且它们每一个都是
completely independent,
operates on its own.
完全独立的，可以独自行动的小MVC。
Doesn't even know,
这时它就是一个
it's a generic reusable view
like thing at this point.
普通的可重用的view之类的东西，
Doesn't even know that
it's in a tab bar.
它甚至不知道它在标签栏中。
Okay, it just knows that
it's supposed to do
它只知道它应该做
whatever it does.
这些事情。
And so
it's modular in that way.
所以在这方面，它是模块化的。
You can also see that there's
no communication between any
可以看到这里不再有其他箭头，
other, there's no other
arrows, except for
除了一些模型。
some of the models.
You see some of the models are
communicating with each other.
某些模型之间在互相通信。
You know a big
要知道，
application might have
a single shared model.
一个大型的应用也许会有一个单独的共享模型。
Or the models might be split
off into pieces to be used by
或者，模型会被分开来供子MVC使用。
sub MVCs.
Okay?
But
但是，
that's the only kind of
communication you have there.
这里只能使用这种通信方式。
All other communication is
其它所有的通信
either the structure view
communication we saw on MVC,
要么是MVC中的结构化通信，
or it's using MVCs as part
of the view of another MVC.
要么是将MVC用作另一个MVC视图的一部分。
Any question about that?
有问题吗？
So we definitely don't want
to be having designs that
所以我们当然不希望设计成这样，
look like this, okay?
Where everybody's
talking to everybody.
所有都在互相通信，
We can't tell who's
talking to what.
我们不能分清谁在和什么通信。
It's just impossible to debug
a program like this, and
这会让调试程序变得异常艰难，
it doesn't scale.
而且它无法规模化。
You can't build really
big programs this way.
你不能通过这种方式创建出大程序。
It just becomes impossible to
这样的话，
know how touching anything
would break everything, right?
你无法弄清楚，什么地方会引发整个程序的崩溃。
So we're definitely not
going to be doing that.
所以我们绝对不会这样做的。
All right so that's MVC and,
所以，这就是MVC，
like I say, on Monday we'll
apply MVC to our calculator.
我们将会在周一的课里把MVC应用到我们的计算器程序中。
So what's coming up?
所以，接下来是什么？
I always try to get to
this slide every lecture.
我每节课都尽量讲到这里，
Sometimes I forget but
it's posted in the slides.
有时我会忘记，但是它被放到了课件中。
It says tomorrow is Friday.
周五也就是明天，
No, day after
tomorrow is Friday.
不对，后天的周五，
And people who
are watching on iTunes U,
在iTunes U上观看的同学们，
these Friday sections will
not be on iTunes U so
周五的部分不会被放到iTunes U上，
don't go looking for
them only the normal Monday,
只有周一和周三的课件才会被放上去，
Wednesday lectures
went on iTunes U.
所以不要到处找。
But, for Stanford students,
但是对于在坐的同学，
Friday we have this debugger
section we talked about.
周五我们将讨论之前谈到的调试部分。
And then next Monday,
下周一，你们的阅读作业
your reading assignment
is gonna be due.
将会截至。
In other words,
you should be done with that
换句话说，你应当在周一上课之前
reading assignment before
the start of Monday's lecture.
完成阅读作业。
And I'm gonna assign you
another reading assignment.
我会再布置给你们一个阅读作业。
It might be your only
other reading assignment.
它将会是你们最后一个阅读作业。
Perhaps there'll be
a reassignment three,
也许以后还会有阅读作业，
but it won't be any
more than that.
但是不会像那个一样多。
And then on Wednesday I'm
下周三，我会深入介绍
really gonna dive into
swift and foundation.
Swift语言和Foundation框架。
I'm gonna talk a little bit
about the Objective C legacy,
我将会介绍一点遗留下来的Objective-C。
and then your assignment
one is gonna be
你们的作业一将会在
due a week from today.
一周后截至。
It's been posted for you, and
your assignment two is gonna
你们已经看到了，作业二将会在
go out next Wednesday and be
due the Wednesday after that.
下周三布置下去，下下周三截至。
Just for a little bit of
advanced planning for
提前为你们所有人
all of you.
做一些计划。
Okay?
Any other questions?
还有问题吗？
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
>> For more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.
>> 想了解更多，请登录 stanford.edu